Finding Aid for Michigan Leaders in Community Health Nursing Oral History Project records, 1986-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Leaders in Community Health Nursing Oral History Project records 1986-1997
Michigan Leaders in Community Health Nursing Oral History Project.
1.3 linear foot
9984 Bimu 2
Oral history project focused on elder public health and community health nurses. Project leader Stephanie Myers Schim completed a dissertation based on the interviews. Administrative files on the project, background material on interviews, audio cassette tapes, transcripts of some interviews, and articles on the project including the dissertation "Leadership Expression of Elder Community Health Nurse Leaders in Michigan."
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Stephanie Myers Schim in January 1998 (Donor no. 8667 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
In 1986, Stephanie Myers Schim began work on the "Michigan Leaders in Community Health Nursing" oral history project, part of what would eventually become her dissertation research for the Ph.D. in nursing at Wayne State University in Detroit, Michigan. The oral history project targeted elder community/public health nurses in Michigan as the subjects for interviews. The goal for this research was to discover what led these women to pursue nursing as a career, identify what leadership roles they played, and how their profession and jobs changed throughout the years.
The in-depth interviews were conducted by Schim and other nurses and uncovered the personal and professional motivations which drew these women to their careers. The interviews reveal the leadership roles taken on by the nurses within the community health care system. Topics include the changing nature of and the treatment of nurses in their jobs, to how they went about facilitating change within their communities for better health care and education.
The information gathered by Schim and her associates resulted in a published article and Schim's dissertation. The article entitled "Uniting the Past and the Future in Public Health Nursing: The Michigan Oral History Project" by Marie F. Gates, Stephanie M. Schim, and Lillian Ostrand, was published in Public Health Nursing, December 1994. Schim's dissertation "Leadership Experiences of Elder Community Health Nurse Leaders in Michigan," was completed and accepted in 1997.
The Michigan Leaders in Community Health Nursing oral history project material consists of three series: Documentation and Research, Publication and Dissertation, and Audio Materials. The records date from 1986 to 1997.
Subjects:
Community health nursing--Michigan.; Nurses--Michigan.; Public health nursing--Michigan.; Oral history.; Schim, Stephanie Myers.; Schim, Stephanie Myers--Leadership experiences of elder community health nurse leaders in Michigan.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Community health nursing--Michigan.; Nurses--Michigan.; Public health nursing--Michigan.; United States. Army. General Hospital Unit, 298th.
Contributors: Sound recordings
Acheson, Phyllis.; Bevan, Elaine.; Brown, A. Josephine.; Chabut, Jean.; Clark, Helen.; Cole, Verna.; Corriveau, Claire.; Dietrich, Gertrude Levandoski.; Fisher, Winifred.; Freliga, Mary.; Gage, Lois Waite.; Grigg, Elizabeth S.; Hatfield, Patricia.; Kurtagh, Cathryn.; Milio, Nancy.; Ostrand, Lillian G.; Paustian, Bonita.; Reid, Doris.; Robeson, Kathryn A.; Scott, Jessie.; Shetland, Margaret L.; Sexton, Mary.; Smith, Gloria R., 1934-; Stewart, Cynthia Jean.; Vander Woude, Florence.; Walsh, Patricia M., 1910-1998.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Sound recordings.
- Documentation and Research
  The Documentation and Research series deals with the collection of information from the interviewers and subjects. This includes correspondence before and after the interview, release forms, background information on the nurses, outlines of interviews, and photographs of the interviewees. Some of the files contain miscellaneous historical documents supplied by the subjects of the interviews. In 1996 Schim conducted a second round of interviews in conjunction with her dissertation research. Transcripts from these second interviews are included in the files. Interviews with transcripts are indicated in the inventory. For the interviews without transcripts, the outlines contain a general index of the wide variety of subjects covered on the cassette tape. For example, the interview outline with Florence Vander Woude indicates a discussion of her involvement with the University of Michigan affiliated 298th General Hospital unit during World War II in addition to discussion of her career in community health.
  - Interview and Background Information
    - Phyllis Acheson 1988 (Box 1)
    - Elaine Bevan 1988, 1996 (Box 1)
      (includes transcript)
    - A. Josephine Brown 1987, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Jean Chabut 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Helen Clark 1988 (Box 1)
    - Verna (Mickie) Cole 1993 (Box 1)
    - Claire Corriveau 1988 (Box 1)
    - Gertrude Levandoski Dietrich 1992, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Winifred Fisher 1986 (Box 1)
    - Mary Freliga 1996 (Box 1)
    - Lois Gage 1991 (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth S. Grigg 1992 (Box 1)
    - Patricia Hatfield 1988 (Box 1)
    - Cathryn Kurtagh 1992 (Box 1)
    - Nancy Milio 1994 (Box 1)
    - Lillian Ostrand 1986 (Box 1)
    - Bonita (Bonnie) J. Paustian 1996 (Box 1)
    - Kay Phelan 1990 (Box 1)
    - Doris E. Reid 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kathryn Robeson 1986 (Box 1)
    - Jessie Scott 1987 (Box 1)
    - Margaret Shetland 1996 (Box 1)
    - Mary Sexton 1988 (Box 1)
    - Gloria Richardson Smith 1996 (Box 1)
    - Cynthia Stewart 1992 (Box 1)
    - Florence Vander Woude 1989 (Box 1)
    - Patricia Walsh 1990 (Box 1)
  - Index to Cassette Tapes (Box 1)
  - Interviews Pending 1989-1994 (Box 1)
  - Oral History Interviewing Manuals 1985, 1988 (Box 1)
- Publication and Dissertation
  The series Publication and Dissertation contains the end product of the research conducted by Stephanie Schim and those who assisted her. This consists of the published article, "Uniting the Past and the Future in Public Health Nursing: The Michigan Oral History Project" and Schim's dissertation, "Leadership Experiences of Elder Community Health Nurse Leaders in Michigan."
  - "Uniting the Past and the Future in Public Health Nursing: The Michigan Oral History Project" by Marie F. Gates, Stephanie M. Schim, and Lillian Ostrand Public Health Nursing, December 1994 (Box 1)
  - "Leadership Experiences of Elder Community Health Nurse Leaders in Michigan," Dissertation by Stephanie M. Schim 1997 (Box 1)
- Audio Materials
  The Audio Materials series includes tapes of the interviews Schim and her assistants conducted and an index to the tapes. This index cross-matches the numbers on the tapes to the person who was interviewed, and those who assisted and/or conducted the interviews. The tapes themselves are labeled with the names of nurses who participated in the interviews.
  - Audio Tapes of Interviews, 54 audiocassettes (Box 2)